A Guide to the Gordon and Webster Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr.
  - Subseries B. General Correspondence (Box-folder 2:1-11:6)
    - 1931 Gordon family correspondence, 20 items (Box-folder 8:5)
      Armistead’s father wrote that Dr. Joseph DeJarnette at Western State diagnosed Armistead’s sister, Margaret with tuberculosis. It was mentioned that Scott stadium was not properly braced and a section of it had sunk before it had even been used. Armistead’s father passed away (October?) several months after Edwin Anderson Alderman (April). (Classes were suspended for Alderman’s funeral) Correspondence from the death of Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr. can be found in Series I Armistead Churchill Gordon, General Correspondence Box: 2 Folder: 7. James wrote that he was thankful for his new job as an accountant for the City. He also wrote about hard times and that his salary was going to pay overdue grocery bills.
    - 1932 Gordon family correspondence, 23 items (Box-folder 8:6)
      Armistead and James wrote to their sister Mary about visiting her, installing a telephone for her, buying property in Charlottesville, selling their father’s books and updates on their daily lives.
    - 1933 Gordon family correspondence, 25 items (Box-folder 9:1)
      James wrote that the only bank in Lexington, North Carolina “had closed up.” Armistead was working on a biography of John Hartwell Cocke. He (Armistead) mentioned that Phillippa Bruce was to marry Arch Shepperson. James and Armistead wrote about prohibition and alcohol tax in North Carolina.
    - 1934-1935 Gordon family correspondence, 12 items (Box-folder 9:2)
      James mentioned infantile paralysis; and the cotton mill strike hurting business in Lexington. There are also cases of infantile paralysis in Charlottesville and Armistead wrote that there was so much concern some parents were taking their children out of the area. He also mentioned taking trips with Fiske Kimball to Bremo (home of General Cocke as Armistead was working on a manuscript about Cocke. There is a newspaper clipping of an obituary for Nannie Jacquelin Minor (1874-1934) daughter of John B. Minor. Included are letters from Ann Gordon.
    - 1936-1937 Gordon family correspondence, 24 items (Box-folder 9:3)
      Armistead and Cornelia took a trip to Charleston, South Carolina and Lexington, North Carolina. James was working as the City Manager. Included in the correspondence are letters from Ann Gordon, her cousins, ("Gordie" and "Bill") and (Aunt) Mary Gordon
    - 1938 Gordon family correspondence, 17 items (Box-folder 9:4)
      There is a letter from Armistead to Mary and Scribners Magazine about permission to use part of his father's story for teaching purposes, and Armistead mentioned the death of his friend, John Luck.
    - 1939 Gordon family correspondence, 13 items (Box-folder 9:5)
      Armistead and James wrote to Mary about their busy lives. Armistead and Cornelia were taking Ann to the World's Fair in New York.
    - 1940-19431951n.d. Gordon family correspondence, 8 items (Box-folder 9:6)
      There are letters from James and his wife Adelaide about the family and their health including a description of their daughters, Mary Gordon ("Gordie") and Adelaide Gordon, "Bill." In 1951 James wrote his sister, Mary that he took out a loan so that he could pay off her mortgage for her.
    - 1942 August-September Gordon family correspondence: Cornelia to Armistead, 20 items (Box-folder 9:7)
      Cornelia wrote to Armistead while he was stationed in Washington, D. C. during the war and at Cambridge, Massachusetts where he was training.
    - 19461949 Gordon family correspondence: James to Armistead, 4 items (Box-folder 9:8)
      James wrote to Armistead and Cornelia about his new veneer business, and that he hoped to be able to attend Ann Gordon's wedding
    - 1923-1924 Book reviews: "Virginian Writers of Fugitive Verse", 9 items (Box-folder 10:1)
      There are reviews about Armistead's book from the Literary Digest, Virginia Historical Magazine, UVA Alumni News, Alumni Bulletin (Philip Alexander Bruce,) Virginia Law Register, Philadelphia Public Ledger, and the Boston Evening Transcript
    - 1942 Financial papers of Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr., 2 items (Box-folder 10:2)
      There is a legal agreement designating trust funds for Ann Gordon and a lease agreement for a tenant at 1616 Jefferson Park Avenue
    - 1937-1956 Financial papers of Mary Daniel Gordon, 9 items (Box-folder 10:3)
      There is a trust fund settlement of Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr., and a deed of trust for the Gordon house on Beverly Street in Staunton
    - 1960-1972 Financial papers of Mary Daniel Gordon, 16 items (Box-folder 10:4)
      There are real estate and insurance papers pertaining to rental properties
    - 1782-1923 Genealogy: Coleman family, 4 items (Box-folder 10:5)
      There is a copy of a will for James Lindsay from 1782 that leaves instructions about the sale of his slaves; a Coleman Farming Record; and correspondence from 1894 about the Coleman and Lindsay side of the family
    - 1882-1890 Genealogy: Daniel family, 5 items (Box-folder 10:6)
      There are miscellaneous postcards to the members of the Daniel's family about their health.
    - 1913-1948 Genealogy: Gordon Family, 8 items (Box-folder 10:7)
      Included is a letter from George Gordon Battle, Sr. describing his relationship as first cousin to Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr. and the closeness of their families. There are also photographs of tombstones for the Fitzhugh Gordons and letters requesting copies of Gordon books on genealogical information. Also included are [unknown] family letters from 1893
    - n. d. Genealogy tree, 1 item (Box-folder 10:8)
    - n. d. Miscellaneous, 100 items (Box-folder 10:9)
      Included are stamp collections, invitations, typed poetry, an address book, and photographs of Senator Thomas S. Martin, and W. B. McHugh. There is a printed application for Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr. as a candidate for the position of court reporter (1881).
    - Oversize: Certificates of Diploma from Staunton Military Academy, 3 items (Box 10)
    - Oversize: Architectural drawings, 3 items (Box 10)
      There are blueprints for the Gordon family home (for alterations to the house) in Staunton
    - Oversize: certificate for William Webster, 1 item (Box 10)
    - 1920 News clippings, 42 items (Box-folder 10:10)
      There are miscellaneous news clippings about Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr. and a description of Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr. as a great educator, and an engagement announcement for Ann Gordon. There are also numerous clippings about a variety of subjects that interested or amused the Gordons, including cartoons, and recipes.
    - n. d. News clippings about Franklin Delano Roosevelt, 30 items (Box-folder 10:11)
    - n. d. News clipping of an article by William Gordon McCabe, 1 item (Box-folder 10:12)
    - 1920 Schools: Staunton Military Academy, 1 item (Box-folder 10:13)
      There is a miscellaneous article about the death of Colonel William Gibbs Kable (1872-1920,) the head of Staunton Military Academy, and son of its founder, Captain William Hartman Kable (1837-1912)
    - 1915-1918 Schools: Grades, 9 items (Box-folder 10:14)
      There is a University of Virginia completion of courses certificate for James Lindsay Gordon; and College of William and Mary report cards for George Loyall Gordon, Jr.
    - 1941-1952 United States Navy, 39 items (Box-folder 10:15)
      There are certificates including the Certificate of Satisfactory Service; Certificate of appointment as Lieutenant Commander; dog tags; letters of commendation from the Secretary of the Navy, James Forrestal; original orders; Officer's Qualification Record Jacket; and a letter from Gordon to the National Inventors Council in which he suggested the combining of incendiary bomb with explosive bomb as a weapon of offensive-defense. There are also photographs
    - 1942-1951 United States Navy Receipts, 38 items (Box-folder 10:16)
      There are travel reimbursement forms and miscellaneous information on uniforms, payroll, and training
    - 1921; 1931-1936 UVA: Minutes of the Board of the University of Virginia, 8 items (Box-folder 10:17)
      Included is a resolution to honor Edwin Anderson Alderman at his passing; minutes from 1933 regarding the Board of Visitors failure to appoint a new president; a letter from the faculty recommending John Lloyd Newcomb as president to the Rector and Board of Visitors; included are handwritten notes about general faculty procedures and a list of teachers, or "officers of instruction"
    - 1969 UVA: Dedication to James Southall Wilson by Fredson Bowers, 1 item (Box-folder 10:18)
    - 1918-19191942 World War I and World War II documents, 7 items (Box-folder 10:19)
      Included are documents and correspondence from the Gas Defense Division, Chemical Warfare Service of the War department. There are notices to appear for physical examination; promotion letter; honorable discharge; and a letter from President John Lloyd Newcomb granting Gordon a leave of absence from his professorial duties to take his commission as a lieutenant in the United States Naval Reserve.
    - n. d. Gordon Photographs, 35 items (Box-folder 11:1)
      There are photographs of Armistead, Cornelia, James, Margaret, Mary, Ann Gordon (including her wedding,) and many relatives and friends. There is also a photograph of the Aviator statue after it was first placed in front of the library.
    - 1896n.d. Gordon Photographs, 75 items (Box-folder 11:2)
      Included are Margaret Douglas Gordon, Mary Daniels Gordon, Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr., and Maria Breckinridge Catlett Gordon
    - 1885n.d. Gordon Photographs, 25 items (Box-folder 11:3)
      Included are pen pals from France, Armistead and Cornelia, Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr., John Gordon [1885;] John A. [Lynney;] Lyon Gardiner Tyler; two portraits of Reuben Lindsay by St. Menin,
    - n. d. Gordon Photographs, 100 items (Box-folder 11:4)
    - n. d. Oversize: Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr., 2 photographs (Box 11)
      One where he is a young man with [colleagues] and another in which he is seated on the lawn with nine men (Board of Visitors?)
    - n. d. Oversize [James Lindsay Gordon?], 1 photograph (Box 11)
    - n. d. Oversize: photograph of Edwin Anderson Alderman, 1 item (Box 11)
    - n. d. Gordon negatives of Florida, 100 items (Box-folder 11:5)
    - 19221932 Gordon negatives, 60 items (Box-folder 11:6)
      [Armistead and Cornelia in Europe and pictures of Ann at age2?]
- Series II: William Webster
  - n. d.1972 United States Atomic Energy Commission, 3 items (Box-folder 12:1)
    There is a document titled, "Reasons for Supporting a Minimum Shelter Program of Protection from Fallout" marked "secret" in pencil with notes by William Webster. There are also memos from the General Advisory Committee about the role of the AEC.
  - 1957-1972 Awards, 70 items (Box-folder 12:2)
    There is a letter (and negative) from President Richard M. Nixon to William Webster congratulating him on winning the John Fritz Medal Board of Award. (Original is in vault) There are press releases, a banquet program, and numerous congratulations as well as thank you letters from Webster. He was also named outstanding engineer in 1964 from the Engineering Societies of New England, Inc. There is a resolution of the Yankee Atomic Electric Company recorded with profound sorrow the death of William Webster; an Atomic Energy Commission Citation; and excerpts and poems about William Webster.
  - 1957-1972 Business property: Bailey Island, Maine, 23 items (Box-folder 12:3)
    Bailey Island is located in Weld, Maine and was bought by William Webster as an investment and a shared a vacation spot with the Fletcher family. Included is a deed for parcel of land on Bailey Island to Abbott and Eileen Fletcher for one dollar; deed to Avery M. Fides; and letters from Abbott and Eileen Fletcher and the Webster's. There is also an article about Yankee Power Company by Abbott Fletcher, and Weld maps and newsletters.
  - 1951-1969 Business property: Cool Branch Farm, Churchville, Maryland, 15 items (Box-folder 12:4)
    With the help of his brother, Steve Webster, William Webster purchased Cool Branch Farm with Steve Close;(who paid a much smaller percentage) Included are descriptions of the costs of farm contents; map and photographs of the farm; and letters between William Webster and Steve and Beverly Close.
  - 1952-1972 Business property: Cool Branch Farm Expenses, 42 items (Box-folder 12:5)
    Description of cows and heifers with detailed alphabetical names, and costs; lists of receipts and income.
  - 1952-1971 Business property: Cool Branch Farm Tax Returns, 28 items (Box-folder 12:6)
    Income tax returns for the farm
  - 1967-1969 Business: Huyck Corporation, 6 items (Box-folder 12:7)
    Article about William Webster being elected Chairman of the Board in 1967; correspondence from Rodney T. Clarke outlining travel arrangements for William Webster
  - 1948 July 27 Business: List of names for government positions, 1 item (Box-folder 12:8)
    Booklet of names of [government] employees or potential employees and notes [by William Webster] about their individual strengths related to employment in various government positions.
  - 1953-1957 Business: National Security Resources Panel (Gaither Committee), 13 items (Box-folder 12:9)
    National security report marked secret security document written by CIA representatives and chemical and electric company executives appointed by the President of the United States, to study National Security. Included are the minutes from meetings and a draft of a report by William Webster; a list of names for the Army Scientific Advisory Panel (September 10, 1956;) a presentation by the Security Resources Panel to the National Security Council Program marked "secret" (November 7, 1957) a thank you letter to William Webster from Robert Cutler on behalf of the President of the United States, Dwight D. Eisenhower; and a press release telegram. Other correspondents include William L. White, Stanford Research Institute; Horace Rowan Gaither, Jr.; Gordon Gray, Office of Defense Mobilization; Robert Sprague; and William C. Foster, Office of Defense Mobilization; and [James Phinney Baxter,] President of Williams College, Williamstown, Massachusetts. There is a list of Gaither Associates; and an Army Scientific Advisory Panel printed booklet.
  - 1935 July Business: New England Power Association, 1 item, 48 typewritten pages (Box-folder 12:10)
    There is a report titled, "The Market for the Domestic Use of Electricity" which is a survey of the market situation with recommendations for the executives and company managers.
  - 1959-1968 Business: Rand Corporation, 4 items (Box-folder 12:11)
    There is an article from the Rand Corporation newsletter, The Random News, about William Webster being elected to replace Horace Rowan Gaither as Chairman of Rand; a list of Rand trustees with biographies; and a list of attendants for 1967 and 1968 meetings.
  - 1945-1951 Business: Research and Development Board of the United States National Defense, 46 items (Box-folder 12:12)
    There are notes by William Webster and correspondence (some marked secret) and reports related to his work with the Military Liaison Committee and as Director of the Research and Development Board of the Defense Department. Included are Webster's personal goals for his role in the group; a certificate of participation; reports written by Webster; and many thank you letters to Webster. Correspondents include David E. Lilienthal, Chairman U. S. Atomic Energy Commission; James Forrestal, Secretary of Defense; J. E. Hull, Lieutenant General, Office of the Secretary of Defense; Art Davis, Rear Admiral United States Navy, Director, Joint Chiefs of Staff; George F. Kennan, The Counselor, Department of State; George T. Felbeck, Vice President, Carbide and Carbon Chemicals Corporation; [Joe,] The Chief of Staff, U. S. Army; and William T. Golden. There is a letter from Louis Johnson offering Webster the chairmanship on behalf of President Truman telling him that they would not take no for an answer.
  - n. d. Business: Yankee Atomic Energy Plant, 1 item (Box-folder 12:13)
    Paper by William Webster on "Planning and Financing a Nuclear Plant"
  - Oversize: Certificates from the U. S. Navy, MIT, and President Nixon and Truman for his service in the Department of Defense; also certificate for admission to a Fraternity, 10 items (Box 12)
  - 1960-1977 Charities, 17 items (Box-folder 12:14)
    There are letters and information about donations from William Webster, including a scholarship for the boys at Saint James School, and contributions to the memory of Horace Rowan Gaither, Jr. at Harvard Medical School.
  - 1963-1966 Charities: Chapel at St. James School, 17 items (Box-folder 12:15)
    Programs from the ceremony to start building a chapel in memory of Eleanore Blodgett Webster and letters about Webster donating up to ninety thousand dollars for the chapel.
  - 1961-19641972 Charities: Emmanuel Episcopal Church, 6 items (Box-folder 12:16)
    There are letters from Stevenson Williams Webster about William Webster donating funds for two stained glass windows in the Emmanuel Episcopal Church in Bel Air, Maryland. There is also a letter from Lewis F. Cole, Jr. about William Webster's funeral service.
  - 1917-1946 Correspondence of Webster, Blodgett, and Foster Families, 53 items (Box-folder 13:1)
    Mostly there are family letters of Eleanore and William Webster, his brother Stevenson Williams Webster ("Steve") and their parents and grandparents. Eleanore and William wrote to Eleanor's parents, Edward ["Peter'] and Alice Blodgett describing the birth of their son, Richard Henry ("Harry") Webster. Steve Webster wrote about the financial struggles of their mother and sister in 1933. There are also letters from William Webster's son, Harry Webster to the Blodgetts (his maternal grandparents) about his service in World War II in Texas, Oklahoma, Hawaii, and Japan from 1943 to 1946. There is a letter from William Webster's father about having to sell his store and the difficulties of finding a job. (1932) [Poem by Eleanor Blodgett Webster in 1908?]
  - 1947-1951 Correspondence of Webster, Blodgett, and Foster Families, 27 items (Box-folder 13:2)
    There are letters from Eleanore describing her trip to the west coast. There are letters from Elanore's parents, Peter and Alice Blodgett to Harry, his wife Ann Gordon Webster and their new son, William "Barney" Webster. According to an enclosed itinerary, William Webster was scheduled to meet Colonel Fred Clarke, Colonel E. B. Kelly, Lieutenant Colonel S. L. Stewart, and Colonel Arthur H. Frye, Jr. in California, and Washington State about work on national security and atomic energy. In his notes, he mentioned that J. Robert Oppenheimer was away from Berkeley until May. (1947)
  - 1933-1972 General correspondence William Webster, 30 items (Box-folder 13:3)
    There is correspondence between William Webster and his secretary (and second wife,) Vollie Sanderson about his itineraries, business meetings, stock prices, and settlements of business and family affairs. There is a letter from Paul B. Metcalf who wrote about being stationed in London with the blackouts, and mentioned his sympathy for the British, and the high wages received by the American Army as compared to the British (1944). There is a letter about William T. Golden in which Golden suggested that Webster look into Delhi-Taylor Oil controlled by the Murchison's who wanted to liquidate it in 1963. Some correspondents include John A. Lynney; Lewis L. Strauss; Donald F. Chamberlain; Alva B. Morgan; and Steven W. Close.
  - 1951-1953 General correspondence Mr. and Mrs. William and Eleanore Webster, 20 items (Box-folder 13:4)
    Lydia and Ivor Rees (pen pals from South Wales, Britain) corresponded with Mrs. Webster about rations, the high prices and scarcity of goods in Britain, updates on her husband and daughters, and appreciation to Mr. and Mrs. Webster for the parcels of food that Eleanore continually sent them.
  - 1954-1961 General correspondence Mr. and Mrs. William and Eleanore Webster, 34 items (Box-folder 13:5)
    There are more letters from Lydia and Ivor Rees thanking them for food and clothes and comparing news about their grandchildren.
  - 1963 General correspondence of Mrs. Vollie Sanderson Webster, 4 items (Box-folder 13:6)
    Congratulation letters on Vollie's engagement and marriage to William Webster.
  - 19491964 Correspondence Hope Ariel Harlan, 17 items (Box-folder 13:7)
    First cousin of Harry Webster (niece of William Webster and daughter of his sister, Ariel Webster Harlan) wrote to Harry and Ann and Aunt Eleanore and Uncle Bill Webster about her activities in school and later about her own family.
  - n. d. Correspondence Tina Anderson, 26 items (Box-folder 14:1)
    Webster family member
  - 1961196419661974 Correspondence Mrs. Miles H. Wolff (Nan), 37 items (Box-folder 14:2)
    Anna Stump Webster Wolff ("Nan") was one the two sisters of William Webster and Stevenson W. Webster. Included are two letters from Nan to Vollie Sanderson Webster; an article about Nan, and her family attending an event at the White House with President Lyndon Johnson and Lady Bird Johnson to honor her husband, Miles for becoming President of the American Society of Newspaper Editors and his colleagues. There is an obituary marking the death of Nan, dated March 4, 1974.
  - 1955 V. I. P. Correspondence, 2 items (Box-folder 14:3)
    There is a handwritten note from President Eisenhower to William Webster sending love to Harry's son, "Barney, and a letter from President Richard M. Nixon to William Webster (See Awards Box: 11 Folder: 2). Originals are in vault.
  - 1972 Correspondence: Letters of sympathy for William Webster's death, 116 items (Box-folder 14:4)